A funeral cortége clatters its way
through the cobbled streets of Brussels.
殡仪队嗒嗒地通过布鲁塞尔的鹅卵石街道
Inside the carriage is the body
殡仪车里，躺着有史以来最有影响力的
of the most powerful French painter
there had ever been.
法国画家，雅克路易大卫
Jacques-Louis David.
的遗体。
Following the carriage
is a solemn procession of art students,
艺术生们肃穆地跟随在殡仪车后面，手举招牌，
holding up placards
with the names of his paintings.
上书这位画家的平生作品名称。
All but one, which happened to be
the greatest of them all.
但是，刚好是最杰出的一副，却偏偏未在其中。
It was a picture which hadn't seen
the light of day for 30 years.
尘封三十年期间
No one, least of all the man who painted it,
dared show it.
包括画家本人在内，没人敢于展示它。
No wonder. It was the most spellbinding thing
he had ever made.
也不奇怪。这是大卫最富魔力的作品，
A painting before which people had once swooned.
人们在它面前激动晕厥
A painting both beautiful and repulsive.
它美丽动人而又惹人厌恶
But the picture was also a guilty secret,
但这副画作还是一个罪恶的秘密，
the real reason why David's body
was refused burial in France.
它才是大卫的遗体被拒绝葬在法国的原因。
So, what was it about this painting
那么，究竟是什么使这幅画
which made it both his unforgettable
masterpiece and his unforgivable crime?
成为大卫难以忘怀的经典，
同时又是他无可原谅的罪恶？
On the 19th September, 1783,
1783年9月19日，
an enormous taffeta spheroid
wobbled its way unsteadily
一个巨大的塔夫绸气球摇摇晃晃地
above the palace of Versailles.
升上凡尔赛宫上空。
In the basket were a sheep, a duck and a rooster.
气球篮子里，装着一只羊，
一只鸭子和一只公鸡。
When a violent gust of wind made a tear
near the top of the balloon,
一阵猛风吹来，扯破了气球顶部，
there were fears for the barnyard aeronauts.
人们不禁为农庄飞行员感到担心
In the end, though, the balloon survived
and it was judged the animals had not suffered.
好在，气球最终幸存下来，动物们有惊无险。
This was, though, a major breach of protocol.
但是，此事打破常规：
Versailles had been built to control spectacle.
凡尔赛宫就是为了控制奇观而建，
That way, the mystery of absolutism
was preserved.
非如此无以保持专制的神秘。
On the ground, it was still, to some extent,
an aristocratic vision.
表面上，凡尔赛在一定程度上仍然是一派贵族景象
In the air, it'd become democratic.
但是空气里弥漫着民主的气息。
In Paris, a more down-to-earth thrill.
而在巴黎，有一种更加世俗的狂欢
Beaumarchais'play, The Marriage of Figaro,
is about to open after several government bans.
博马舍的喜剧，费加罗的婚礼，
在多次被禁之后，要开演了。
The king had called it detestable.
That guaranteed a crowd.
国王说这出戏可鄙可恨。这票房就有了保障了。
No, monsieur.
>> 不不，大人，
Because you are a great lord,
you think you're a great genius?
>> 就因为你是大老爷，你就该是一个大天才？
Nobility, rank,
>> 爵位，品衔，
position, fortune,
how proud they make a man feel.
>> 职级，财富，
>> 它们让人何其得意
What have you done to deserve such advantages?
>> 你有何德能配得如此眷顾？
Put yourself to the trouble of being born,
nothing more. For the rest...
>> 无非是投对了胎，除此之外，
...you're a very ordinary man.
>> 你不过就是个普通人
There were no signs
that the bravos died on the lips of the nobility,
即使在贵族圈子里，赞美也一点不少，
even as they began to realise
the significance of the attack.
即使他们开始意识到这种攻击的严重性
Talk about signing your own death warrant.
要说这就叫自掘坟墓的话
But then, how were they to know that,
in under 10 years,
那谁又能料到，不到十年
they'd be on the receiving end
of something far more wounding than words.
贵族们将领教远比言辞更具伤害性的攻击呢
Look, citizens,
>> 看吧，公民们
at the glorious destiny that awaits us.
>> 光荣的使命等待着我们
You have a whole nation to mobilise.
>> 整个民族等着我们去动员
No more...
>> 不再……
Still, the French Revolution
could never have happened
尽管如此，如果没有这种戏剧感，
without this sense of theatre.
法国大革命就不会发生。
Its great orators, like Danton, were performers,
shamelessly playing to the gallery,
当时那些重要的演说家们，比如Danton，同时也是表演者，
毫不含糊地迎合大众趣味
milking the cheers and the hisses.
以榨取欢呼和嘘声
Reason fights on your side,
>> 理性站在你这一边！
and you have not even begun
to astonish the world.
>> 而你，尚未开始你震撼世界的征程！
And if they were really
going to create a new France,
而如果要创立一个全新的法兰西
they needed someone to create images
to go with the words.
他们就需要一个能够用画面阐释文字的人
That someone was Jacques-Louis David.
这个人就是雅克路易大卫
It was David who would give people
the vision of what a true citizen was.
是大卫给了大众理想公民的图景
His art, then, wasn't meant as gallery fodder.
It was an entire way of life.
因此，他的艺术本不是为了充实画廊，
而是一种全新的生活方式，
Or death.
或者死亡方式。
I'm not sure how I feel about this painting,
except deeply conflicted.
除了深深的冲突感，我不知道还能怎么描述我的感受。
Yes, it's tragically beautiful.
不错，它有着悲剧般的美感
But to say that is to separate it
from the appalling moment of its creation.
但是这样说，就完全抛开了可怕的创作背景。
This is Jean-Paul Marat,
the most paranoid of the Revolution's fanatics.
画中人是让-保尔马拉，大革命中最为偏执的狂热分子
He's been assassinated in his bath.
他在浴缸中被人刺杀
Marat was someone for whom there could
never be enough terror, never enough killing.
对马拉来说，手段多恐怖都不算什么，杀多少人都不够
But for David, Marat isn't a monster. He's a saint.
但在大卫看来，马拉不是杀人狂魔，而是圣徒。
This painting transforms Marat
into a paragon of virtue.
这幅油画把马拉变成了道德模范。
Breathtaking? For sure.
叹为观止？当然了
But maybe also just a little mad.
但是也有一点疯狂吧
Which isn't to say that Jacques-Louis David
was some sort of malevolent crackpot.
这倒不是说雅克路易大卫是恶毒的疯子
All his life, he was really only looking for virtue.
终其一生，大卫都在追求美德。
There was something painfully earnest
about him, resolute, self-contained.
他身上有些痛苦而真诚的特质，果断刚毅，自成一体。
One, two, three.
>> 一，二，三
Not surprising, really. When he was seven,
其实也不奇怪。七岁的时候
his father, an iron merchant,
had been killed in a pistol duel.
他的父亲，一个铁器商人，在一场手枪决斗中被杀
Something iron must have entered the boy's soul.
必定有些铁质的东西进入了小男孩的精神
He was looked after by friendly uncles
他由友好的叔叔们看管
who wanted him to be a lawyer or an architect,
but David would hear of nothing but painting.
叔叔们希望他能成为律师或者建筑设计师，
但是大卫除了油画什么都听不进去。
So the uncles sent him on to his mother's cousin,
所以叔叔们把他送到妈妈的的表亲那里
who just happened to be
the most successful painter in France.
这个表亲刚好是法国最成功的油画家，弗朗索瓦布歇
Francois Boucher knew exactly
what art was supposed to deliver for the nobility.
弗朗索瓦布歇最清楚贵族们想要什么样的艺术了
The pinkest, flossiest eye candy imaginable,
你能想到的最松软粉嫩的秀色佳人
rosy bums romping on frothy pillows.
颜色红润的闲汉与泡沫枕头嬉戏
But perhaps
Boucher saw in the sober, young David
但是或许，布歇从年轻而严肃的大卫身上看到了
someone for whom melting beauty
was not going to be the point of art.
一个不以柔美为艺术追求的人
So he sent him on to another master.
所以他把大卫送到了另一位大师门下。
But Boucher said to David,
''Come and see me from time to time,
但也对大卫说：”经常回来看看，
and I will teach you my warmth.''
我可以教你画出热情。“
But David would never be at home
in the pleasure industry. He was a loner.
但是大卫跟愉悦总是合不来，他总是独来独往。
Once he got involved in a swordfight,
and took a vicious slash on his cheek.
他有一次卷入了一场持剑争斗中，
脸上被狠狠划了一道
The wound grew into a benign tumour.
That was the first thing anyone noticed about him.
伤口后来长成了一个良性肿瘤。
这成了他最显眼的标记
His enemies would call him,
''David with the swollen cheek. ''
他的对手们叫他，肿脸的大卫
Accidents like this happened every day.
Walk down any Paris street or into any salon,
这种事情在当时每天都有，
在巴黎，随便走在哪条街道，或者进入哪个沙龙，
and you would have seen a rich gallery
of the deformed and the disfigured.
都能看到形形色色的容貌毁损，
Terrible smallpox scars, club feet, harelips, the lot.
可怕的天花疤痕，畸形脚，兔唇，不一而足。
But some accidents matter to people
and some don't. This one did.
但是有些外伤对人无关紧要，有些很让人在意。
大卫就很在意自己的伤口。
David's disfigurement meant
he couldn't talk properly.
大卫这种破相意味着他无法正常说话。
Few people could understand what he was saying,
so he ended up not saying very much.
没人能明白他说的是什么，
所以他也就不怎么说话。
When he did talk, he was painfully conscious
of being a stammerer.
说话的时候，他痛苦而清醒地意识到自己的口吃。
If there was ever a moment in history
when wit and banter really mattered,
如果说在历史上有某个时间，机智和诙谐非常重要，
it was surely in 18th-century France.
那肯定就是18世纪的法国了。
But David of the swollen cheek couldn't talk,
he couldn't chat, he just mumbled.
而肿脸的大卫偏偏无法谈论，无法聊天，他只能咕哝。
Maybe there was one consolation,
或许还有一个安慰，
for there was someone else who was famous
for his handicaps in the wit department,
因为当时还有另外一个与机智无缘的知名人士，
and he happened to be the king.
就是当时的国王。
Louis XVI was born to worry about happiness.
路易十六生来就必须为幸福操心
His grandfather, Louis XV,
had designed Versailles around its pursuit.
他的祖父，路易十四，设计了凡尔赛宫。
But for his young successor,
happiness would always be hard work.
但他的继任者而言，幸福快乐很不容易。
When Louis came to the throne in 1775,
he wanted the best for everyone,
当路易于1775年即位时，他希望每个人都好，
but he just didn't know how to get it.
他就是不知道该怎么做
The saddest thing about Louis XVI
关于路易十六，最让人难过的是，
was that the king who went down in history
as the reactionary symbol of the old regime
这个以旧政权反动符号载入史册的国王，
actually thought of himself as thoroughly modern,
deeply into science and technology.
真诚地觉得自己非常现代，
对科学和技术非常感兴趣。
Balloons? Couldn't get enough of them.
气球？怎么也玩不够。
His reign, which ended in catastrophe,
began in a sunburst of giddy optimism,
他的政权，终于灾难，却始于朝阳般令人眩晕的乐观，
and a change in taste, too.
和审美口味的转变。
Out went gold ormolu,
in came modesty, the cult of nature.
金碧辉煌不再吃香，取而代之的是谦逊和对自然的崇拜
Even Louis XVI's young Austrian queen,
Marie Antoinette, was a devotee.
连路易十六的奥地利王后，年轻的玛丽·安托瓦内特，
也是新口味的拥护者。
She built a toy farm here at Versailles,
went off milking cows in the royal dairy.
她在凡尔赛宫建了一个迷你农场，给皇家奶牛挤奶。
So, no more couches and courtesans.
所以，沙发和交际花了不再流行
Instead, tenderness, simplicity.
相反，要柔情，要简洁。
Tears were especially prized
as evidence of feeling.
泪水，作为情感的外显，尤其被珍视。
Paintings like this went down well.
像这种画作就很受欢迎。
Girl Weeping Over Dead Canary
by Jean-Baptiste Greuze.
让 - 巴蒂斯特·格勒兹的
“为死去的金丝雀哭泣的少女”
People wept when they saw it.
人们一边观看一边落泪。
Feelings mattered to David, too,
情感对于大卫也很重要，
but not the shallow kind
embraced by the fashionable elite.
但他所看重的可不是时尚精英们所崇尚的浅薄情感，
No, David was in search of something steelier.
大卫所寻求的，是更为钢劲的情感寄托。
It was amidst the stones of Rome that he found it.
他在罗马城的石头中发现了这种情感寄托，
Everything changed for David here.
Not just what he thought about art,
大卫的一切从此改变了，
不光是他对艺术的看法，
but what he thought
about the future of his country.
还有他对于国家前途的思索。
So what were the stones telling him?
那么，他从这些石头中得到了什么呢？
''This is what happens
to decadent empires, '' they said.
“帝国朽坏，这就是下场”，这些石头仿佛在说
Once there had been a free Rome, the Republic,
曾几何时，自由的罗马共和国，
austere, just, virile, packed with flinty heroes.
严肃，公正，阳刚，到处都是深邃的英雄人物，
But effeminate luxury had killed it.
而最后毁于骄奢淫逸，
Liberty had surrendered to despotism
and the Romans had become slaves.
自由屈服于专制，而罗马人变成了奴隶。
How that message from history
echoed in David's fertile brain.
这些来自历史深处的启示，
是如何在大卫那活跃的大脑里回响呢？
And in 1785, David delivered that message,
在1785年，大卫传达了这个启示，
like a package of bad news
for the complacent and the over-powdered.
给志得意满热衷粉饰者带来了坏消息。
Welcome to the first public art show in the world,
欢迎来到世界上第一次公共艺术展！
in the palace of the Louvre, no less.
展会位于卢浮宫，
This wasn't always a hushed museum.
这可不总是一个安静的博物馆，
Every two years, it staged the greatest
public entertainment in Paris, and it was free.
每过两年，巴黎最盛大的公共娱乐就会在这里上演，完全免费。
Word had got out
there was something sensational to see.
到处都在传说那里有轰动一时的东西可看，
Jacques-Louis David's Oath of the Horatii.
雅克路易大卫的“赫拉迪兄弟之誓”。
It's a painting about a country in crisis.
画的是身处危机的国家，
To avoid war,
the Romans have chosen three of their men
为避免战争，罗马人选了三个男人
to fight with three from the enemy.
Last one standing wins.
与三个敌人决斗，哪方的人最后活下来，就算哪方胜。
The cruel twist is that one of the Roman boys
is married to an enemy girl.
残酷的关键是，其中一个罗马男人已经与敌方的女子成婚。
Widowhood and orphanhood beckon.
要么守寡，要么成孤。
But none of the men
are paying the slightest attention to that.
但是，画面中的男人对此毫不在意
This is a boys' bonding picture,
a tight-packed display of muscle, veins and steel.
这是男孩子们心手相连的图景，
肌肉，静脉和钢刃紧贴在一起
The only splash of colour
is the blood red of that cape.
唯一的大片色彩，是血红色的斗篷。
The father solemnly swears them
to conquer or die,
画中的父亲赤手握着锋利的刀刃，
his naked hand on the sharp blade.
郑重地带他们起誓，要么征服，要么死去。
At least 60,000 people would have come
to the exhibition to see this painting,
至少6万人要去看展出的这幅画，
and not just the bigwigs either,
but shopkeepers, fishwives,
不仅是显要人物，从店主到渔妇，
the whole sweaty, growling public.
整个劳苦大众，
They would be David's people.
他们都是大卫的人民。
And they looked
at that strange line dance of death,
他们看着这种陌生的死亡之舞，
and they didn't know
whether to be thrilled or scared.
不知道该感到激动还是害怕，
It felt like a call to arms
in the face of a great crisis.
仿佛自己身处危机，被召唤入伍。
And that crisis was happening
not in ancient Rome, but here and now,
而危机不在古代罗马，而是就在当下，迫在眉睫，
in Louis XVI's France.
在路易十六的法兰西
It began, as so many revolutions do,
with a financial meltdown.
如同许许多多革命一样，它始于一场金融体系崩溃。
France had taken pride
in helping America to win independence,
帮助美国独立，法国一直引以为傲，
but it had come at a huge cost.
但是也为此付出沉重代价，
Avoiding bankruptcy meant more taxes.
要免于破产，就必须加税，
So, awkward questions were being asked
由此，尴尬的问题被提出来了：
about why the nobility and the clergy
were tax-exempt,
为什么贵族和神职人员可以免税，
while the scarecrow poor
were supposed to empty their pockets.
而穷人却必须掏空口袋？
Wasn't the nation all in it together?
不是该由整个国家来共同承受吗？
The nation? Well, that was a new idea.
整个国家？嗯，这可是个全新的想法。
And while we're at it,
how about elected representatives, too?
既然说到这儿了，是不是该讨论一下民选代表呢？
Oh, it went without saying
that the new France would still be a monarchy.
对了，不用说，新法兰西仍然会是君主政体。
The queen, with all those diamonds,
needed putting in her place,
王后，有那么多钻石了，应该知趣。
but the king was a good fellow.
不过国王人还不错。
No reason to assume a social apocalypse
around the corner.
也没有理由担心什么近在眼前的社会灾难。
For a while, that's how David himself felt,
which didn't mean a little reform wouldn't help.
有一段时间，大卫也是这么感觉的。
但这不是说一点改革都不需要。
There was a lot of deadwood around.
到处都是衰朽之士，
For a start, those non-entities
at the Academy of Painting, they'd have to go.
最起码，绘画学院的那些老朽们，必须滚蛋。
When he was a struggling artist,
they'd rejected him four times.
大卫出名之前，被他们拒过四次。
Now he was successful,
they barely tolerated him.
现在他成功了，他们勉强容忍他。
Well, their time was up.
Anyway, he didn't need them any more.
好了，现在没他们什么事了。
不管怎么说，他也用不着他们。
Now he had intelligent, liberal-minded followers.
现在他有自己聪敏开明的追随者。
Here are two of those good eggs,
rich, smart and affable.
这两位就在其中的佼佼者。
富有，聪明，和蔼可亲
Mr and Mrs Charming,
Antoine and Marie-Anne Lavoisier.
魅力先生和夫人，安东尼和玛丽安，拉瓦锡
He is a famous experimental chemist.
先生是有名的实验化学家，
That flask on the floor is for measuring gases.
地板上的烧瓶是用来测量气体的。
Marie-Anne, who'd married him at 13,
was more than a wife.
女士玛丽安，于13岁嫁给安东尼拉瓦锡。她不仅仅是妻子，
That casual hand on his shoulder
tells us she was a true partner,
随意放在他肩头的手，向我们显示她是一个真正的伴侣，
translating articles from English for him,
designing illustrations for his books.
她为丈夫翻译英文文章，为他的书设计插画。
He's filthy rich,
but he does have a social conscience.
先生财大气粗，却不乏社会良知，
A lot of his money
has been put into draining swamps
把很多钱花在排干沼泽
to eradicate malaria, that sort of thing.
以根除疟疾等事情上。
To look at the portrait,
you'd think David has captured a vision
看着这幅画像，你会觉得大卫捕捉到了一个愿景。
of the kind of people
who ought to be governing France,
正该是像这样人性化，深情而又现代的人
humane, affectionate and modern.
来治理法国。
Well, for 7,000 livres, he wasn't even
going to hint at the other Lavoisier,
当然了，为了7000里弗尔，
他才不会去提及拉瓦锡的另一面，
the one who made money
collecting taxes with the help of a private army.
那个使用私人军队收税而大赚特赚的拉瓦锡。
No, David took his fee, but when the time came
for him to show the painting at the Louvre,
大卫收了他的钱，但是到了要在卢浮宫展示这幅画作的时候，
he ended up withdrawing it.
But then he would, wouldn't he?
大卫却把这幅画抽出来了。肯定会这样的，不是吗？
Between the paint drying and the show opening,
everything in France had changed.
就在油画尚未晾干，展会开幕之前的一段时间里，
法国的一切都变了。
It was 1789.
1789年，
Hope and desperation in equal parts.
希望与绝望并存。
Hope from a representative assembly,
希望来自代表大会，
the Estate's General elected
from thousands of meetings all over France.
代表是由全法国上千次会议选举出来的三级会议代表
But desperation too, because it was happening
at the worst possible time.
绝望，是因为代表大会发生的时刻糟糕至极。
Harvest wipeouts, soaring prices.
庄稼绝收，物价飞涨。
Put hope and desperation together,
and what do you get?
把希望遇到绝望，得到什么？
The political equivalent of nitroglycerine.
政治上的硝化甘油
When the Estate's General met here
in Versailles, in the spring of 1789,
当三级会议于1789年春在凡尔赛集会时，
it all boiled down to one question.
Would the deputies do it the old way,
一切都归结为一个问题：
代表们是应该按照老办法
meeting as three separate orders,
分成贵族，僧侣和平民三个层级开会
nobles, clergy and commoners,
or would they do it the new way,
还是应该用新办法
and for the first time come together
as a single national assembly?
破天荒坐到一起开一个全国大会？
The commoners, among them
a young lawyer, Maximilien Robespierre,
平民代表中，一个叫罗伯斯庇尔的年轻律师，
forced the issue,
迫使人们做出选择，
declaring themselves the only legitimate body,
他声称平民层级才是唯一合法的实体
priests and nobles welcome to join.
欢迎神职人员和贵族加入。
A surprising number of them did.
顺从的神职人员和贵族出人意料的多。
It's the 20th June, 1789,
1789年6月20日，
and it's one of those
late-spring torrential downpours.
在暮春的瓢泼大雨中
And the 600 deputies of the Third Estate,
the commoners,
600多位平民代表
plus their new allies
among the nobles and the clergy,
加上他们在贵族和神职人员中的盟友，
have been locked out of their meeting hall.
被关在会议大厅外边。
A certain Doctor Guillotin
knows a tennis court quite close by.
有个叫吉约丹的医生知道附近有一个网球大厅。
The mayor of Paris, Sylvain Bailly,
is suddenly the star of the show.
巴黎市长，西尔万巴依，突然成了明星。
Swear an oath to God and the fatherland
never to separate,
>> 对上帝和祖国起誓，永不分开
until we have made a sound and just constitution.
>> 直到我们制定出一部健全而公正的宪法。
For the first time, aristocrats,
clergy and bourgeoisie were meeting together
贵族，神职人员和中产阶级第一次
在没有国王许可的情况下,
without the king's permission.
聚在一起。
Arms stretch, bodies embrace,
life had caught up with art.
到处都是伸展的手臂，拥抱的躯体，
现实如艺术般美好，
David's Rome reborn was the new France.
大卫的罗马重生在新法兰西。
A year later, David got to work
on his depiction of the Tennis Court Oath.
一年之后，大卫开始绘制“网球厅宣誓”
It's a picture filled with noise.
The roar of the oath.
画面充满了声音，起誓的声音
The crash of a great electrical storm.
如同电闪雷鸣
The Revolution as an unstoppable force of nature.
革命已经不可阻挡
And at the centre of it all, an enormous space.
在这些的中间，是一个巨大的空间
Except it's not empty at all.
不过并不空虚
It's filled with light and rushing wind,
the furious energy of liberty.
其中充满光亮和疾风，如同自由的能量扫过。
It's an idea.
这是一种信念
An idea so big, it dwarfs the humans who enact it.
这信念如此宏大，投身其中的人显得微不足道。
The drawing was supposed to be
turned into a huge painting.
绘画应该变成一幅巨大的油画。
This is just a small section of it.
But as you can see, it was never finished.
这里只是一种一小部分
但是可以看到，油画一直没有完成。
Before David even had a chance
to put clothes on these nude models,
大卫还没来得及给这些裸体的人物穿上衣服
many of them would be dead or disgraced.
很多在现实中已经死去，或者声名狼藉
The great message of unity and freedom
would soon be quaintly out of date.
团结和自由的启示很快会变得过时
Instead of arms outstretched,
there was an epidemic of finger-pointing.
伸展的手臂，被相互指责所取代
July 1789 ought to have been a moment
of golden optimism for the reborn France.
1789年7月必定是新法兰西历史上最乐观的时刻。
Louis XVI seemed finally to have accepted
the results of the Tennis Court Oath,
路易十六终于接受了网球场宣誓的结果
that there was now a National Assembly in France.
国民议会成立
But here in the Palais Royale,
the Speaker's Corner of Paris,
但是在巴黎皇宫里面，在巴黎的演说广场，
nobody actually believed him.
没人相信路易十六。
People said the king had secretly stocked
the fortress of the Bastille with gunpowder,
有人说国王在巴士底狱的城堡里秘密囤积了火药
so Paris was literally
a powder keg waiting to happen.
所以巴黎就是一个等待爆炸的火药桶
On the morning of July 14th, a crowd
of about 900 converged on the grim fortress.
7月14日早上，大约900人在巴士底狱城堡汇聚
It's always the same, isn't it? Someone panics,
there's a first shot. No one knows from where.
总是这样，对吧？有人突然恐慌，
然后有人，不知道从哪里开了第一枪
Cries of ''Massacre!''
有人喊“大屠杀”
Then, a serious exchange of fire.
接着是一系列交火
It took an afternoon of chaos and 83 lives
before the governor yielded the Bastille.
在一个下午的混乱和83人死亡之后，狱长交出了巴士底狱。
He was promised safe conduct.
他被许诺了安全
What he got
was his head cut off with a fruit knife.
而后被人用水果刀割掉了脑袋。
But then, whoever said revolutions
were going to be bloodless?
不过，谁说过革命会不流血呢？
Here's David's contribution
to the decapitation campaign.
这幅作品是大卫对砍头运动的贡献
It's the darkest thing he ever did.
也是他创作的最暗黑的作品。
It's a Roman father again.
又是一个罗马父亲
Brutus, brooding in the darkness,
在黑暗中沉思的布鲁图斯
has ordered the execution of his sons,
for plotting to bring back the monarchy.
他命令处决了自己的儿子们，因为他阴谋复辟君主制。
Their headless bodies are brought to him,
and he literally doesn't look back.
人们把无头的尸体抬给他，而他就是不回头看。
Only that right foot
is a sign of his repressed emotion.
只有右脚显露出被压制的情感。
Brutus has gone to the dark side.
布鲁图斯在暗处
Light floods the boys' mother,
who sees only her headless children.
光线照在母亲这边，她只能看到孩子们无头的尸身
You feel the tug of the heart.
你几乎可以感觉到心脏的跳动
There's something chilling about this painting,
like all David's great pictures.
如同所有大卫的重要作品一样，这幅画有些地方让人心生寒意
Even as you marvel at its brilliance,
your blood runs cold at what it's saying.
即使在你惊奇于它的绝妙之处的时候，
也不免为其中暗含的信息感到心惊。
Look what's at the dead centre of the picture,
看看画面的中央是什么
a pair of sharp scissors,
the hard, cold metal that's cut the family ties.
一把锋利的剪刀
坚硬，冰冷的金属，随时准备斩断血脉联系。
David seems to have a thing about blades.
大卫对利刃好像有执念
They've marked his face
and now they've marked his mind.
利刃在他的脸上留下了印记，也把印记留在他头脑当中
From father to fatherland is but a short step.
从父亲到祖国只是很小一步
The first two years of the Revolution swung
wildly from mass euphoria to paranoia,
在最初的两年里，大革命从大众狂欢变成无所不在的偏执，
orgies of public hugging,
spasms of vindictive lynching.
从狂喜的公开拥抱，
到战栗的私刑报复。
Why the anger? Because people were still hungry.
为什么愤怒？因为人们还在饿肚子
Bread prices had gone through the roof,
面包价格涨上了天
and people had discovered you couldn't eat votes.
然后人们发现选票不能当饭
Someone was to blame.
一定是谁的错。
''The baker and the baker's wife',
the jeering market women called them,
“面包师和面包师的老婆”，
路易和玛丽被揪出凡尔赛宫的港湾，
as they dragged Louis and Marie Antoinette
out of the safety of Versailles, to Paris.
弄到巴黎的时候，市场上的女人这样叫他们。
The queen, they said,
was no better than an Austrian whore.
他们说，王后简直就是一个奥地利妓女。
David thought the same.
大卫也是这么想的。
''The rioters should have strangled her,
cut the carcass to pieces, ''he wrote.
“暴动的人们应该把她吊死，再碎尸万段。”，他写道
He was at this time
an odd mix of dogma and uncertainty.
在当时，大卫在信条和不确定之间摇摆。
Like millions of his countrymen,
he thought the queen was a monster,
如同千百万法国人一样，他认为王后是个魔头，
but he hadn't given up
on the idea of Louis as citizen king.
但是对于路易成为公民国王，他并未放弃。
He even signed up to do a portrait of him.
他甚至主动要为路易画一幅肖像。
So he was still very much a political ingénue,
所以当时他在政治上还很单纯
until, that is, he met the likes of him.
直到，他遇上了跟自己类似的人。
Jean-Paul Marat, balloonist,
failed inventor, newspaper editor, fanatic.
让保罗马拉，热气球玩家，
失败的发明家，报纸编辑，狂热分子。
Here he is in his bath,
这是他在浴缸里
the only place he could get respite
from the excruciatingly itchy skin disease
只有在这里他才能得到片刻喘息，不再被皮肤病
that left him raw and scaly.
的极端瘙痒折磨到生不如死。
Marat played on hysteria like a drum.
马拉像敲战鼓一样催动这歇斯底里的情绪。
His paper, The Friend of the People,
yelled and cursed and denounced,
他的报纸，“人民之友“，声嘶力竭，谴责诅咒，
ripping off the masks of false patriots
whom he fingered as traitors.
扯下那些被指为叛徒的人们的“爱国面具“
''There are plots everywhere, ''he screamed.
“到处都是阴谋诡计“，他叫喊着
The street, caught between fear and
hyperventilation, ate up the conspiracy theories.
街头的人们，夹在恐惧和过度放松之间，接受了这些阴谋理论。
Marie Antoinette, malevolent slut,
>> 玛丽·安托瓦内特，恶毒的荡妇，
plotting with her brother,
the Emperor of Austria, against France.
>> 伙同他的兄弟，奥地利国王，阴谋反对法国。
Imagine.
>> 发挥你的想象力吧！
Except it was true.
只是，这成真的了。
In June, 1791 , the royal couple was caught
in their escape bid
1791年的6月，王室夫妇在逃跑中被抓住
and taken back, virtual prisoners, to Paris.
然后，像囚犯一样被带回巴黎。
Austria threatened France with dire consequences
should anything happen to the king and queen.
奥地利威胁说如果国王和王后有任何不测，
法国就得承担严重后果。
Now, the royal couple seem like the enemy within.
现在，王室夫妇真的成了内部敌对势力。
The following year, war broke out,
第二年，战争爆发
and their days, and the days
of the French monarchy, were numbered.
他们剩下的日子，法国君主制的日子，就屈指可数了。
Now, fighting for France
meant fighting against royalty.
现在，为法兰西而战自然要反对王室。
Five days after the war started, in April, 1792,
战争爆发五天之后，1792年4月
there was a dinner in the garrison town
of Strasbourg, near the front.
在靠近前线的驻军小镇斯特拉斯堡有一回晚宴，
The idea was to boost
the shaky morale of the army.
用来提高低落的士气
So, there were toasts, there were speeches.
所以现场有干杯，有祝酒词，
''Long live liberty'', ''Death to tyrants'',
the usual thing.
“自由万岁“，”暴君必死“等常见的内容
What was missing, though, was a good song
当时缺少一首好歌
that would send a surge of self-belief
right through the camp.
一首能在营地中激发广泛自信的歌曲
It was Rouget de Lisle,
regimental engineer and part-time composer,
鲁日·德·李尔，一位团工程师和业余作曲家
who came up with that song.
写出了那首歌
You belong to something glorious now.
突然你属于某种荣耀的目标
You belong to the Patrie, the fatherland.
你属于Patrie，属于祖国
MAN: Everything is in motion.
>> 所有的事情都在紧张进行中
Everyone burns to fight. To conquer our enemies,
>> 每个人都急于战斗，去征服敌人
we must have daring, more daring, always daring.
And France will be saved!
>> 我们必须敢于战斗，勇于战斗，永远勇敢，
>> 法兰西必然得到拯救！
In August, 1792, the guards
protecting the royal family were slaughtered,
1792年8月，负责保卫王室家庭的卫兵被杀害。
Louis, Marie Antoinette and their children
were taken to prison.
路易，玛丽和他们的孩子们被投入监狱
One must never compromise with tyrants.
One can only strike at kings through the head.
>> 对暴君绝不可妥协，只能迎头痛击。
I vote for death of the tyrant.
>> 我投处死暴君
You're a very ordinary man.
>> 你不过是个普通人
On January 21st, 1793,
Louis XVI was executed.
1793年1月21日，路易十六被处死。
Among those in the newly formed
National Convention
在新成立的国民大会中
who voted for the death of the monarch,
投票支持处死路易十六的，
was the artist who'd once
taken commissions from him,
有曾经从他那里拿佣金的艺术家
Jacques-Louis David.
雅克-路易 大卫。
So France had been reborn as a republic,
这样，法国重生，变成了共和国。
and David, now a model citizen,
而大卫，现在是模范公民
sat proudly on the benches of the convention
as MP for Paris,
作为巴黎的国会议员， 跟他的
政治偶像马拉和罗伯斯比尔一起，
along with his political idols,
Marat and Robespierre.
骄傲地坐在国民大会的位置上。
There was no going back.
这是一条不归路。
From now on,
David and his art belonged to the Revolution.
从现在起，大卫和他的艺术都属于大革命。
Wherever it lead, he would follow,
哪里需要，他就跟到哪里
and where it lead was dictatorship.
当时需要的是独裁专政
The country was at war,
its enemies were outside and inside France.
国家在战争中，敌人遍布法兰西内外
This was no time for tender feelings.
没有时间温情
Countless people
who had thought of themselves as friends,
无数自以为是革命的朋友而不是敌人的人
not enemies, of the Revolution,
were fingered and denounced.
受到指责和诋毁。
Among the first to be arrested
were his old friends and patrons,
第一批被逮捕的人中，就有他的老朋友和老主顾
Antoine and Marie-Anne Lavoisier.
安托万和玛丽-安妮·拉瓦锡。
She survived the guillotine,
她没上断头台，
he didn't.
他没那么幸运。
For Marat and Robespierre, there could
never be enough guillotined heads to feel safe.
对马拉和罗伯斯比尔来说，杀多少头都不够安全。
In 1789, Marat had called for a few hundred.
1789年的时候，马拉说要杀几百人。
Now, he called for hundreds of thousands.
现在，他要杀几十万人。
Someone had to stop it,
and that someone was Charlotte Corday,
必须要有人阻止他，这时候夏洛特·科迪站了出来，
25 years old, from the town of Caen in Normandy.
25岁，来自诺曼底的
No royalist. A revolutionary, in fact.
她并不是保皇派，反倒是一个革命派。
But a bitter enemy of Marat and his followers.
但是是马拉和其跟随者的激烈反对者。
The dictatorship, she thought,
had made a mockery of the Republic of Liberty.
她认为，专政，是对自由共和国的嘲弄。
She cast herself as a tragic heroine
whose destiny was to save her country.
她把自己投射为注定为拯救国家而牺牲的悲剧女英雄。
On the 9th July, 1793,
Charlotte Corday got on a coach bound for Paris.
1793年7月9日，夏洛特科迪坐上了发往巴黎的长途汽车。
When she arrived,
she came here to the Palais Royale,
到巴黎之后，她来到巴黎皇宫，
bought a black hat with green feathers
and a six-inch knife.
买了一顶带绿色羽毛的黑帽子和一把六英寸的匕首。
In a cheap hotel room, she wrote a speech
在一家经济酒店的房间里，她写下了一篇演说，
explaining why she had to kill Marat
and sewed it to her dress,
解释自己为什么必须刺杀马拉，然后把讲稿
along with her certificate of baptism.
跟她的受洗证书一起，缝进了自己的衣服。
And as Corday was planning the murder,
就在科迪计划刺杀的时候，
David was paying his friend Marat a visit.
大卫正在拜访他的朋友马拉。
He found him propped up in his bath,
他看到他把一个木箱子翻过来临时当桌子，
using an upturned wooden box
as an improvised desk.
在浴缸中撑起身体。
So little time, so many traitors to denounce.
时间紧迫，还有这么多叛徒要谴责
Did the Friend of the People
ever rest from his patriotic toil?
这位人民之友，可曾在爱国辛劳中休息片刻？
The next day, Charlotte Corday walked over
to Marat's house on the rue des Cordeliers.
第二天，夏洛特科迪走过马拉在Cordeliers大街上的住宅。
Barred at the door, she tried delivering
a handwritten note warning him about plots,
被拦在门外，她试图把一个手写的字条交给他，让他警惕一些阴谋，
hoping he was gonna rise to the bait. No reply.
希望他能够上钩。但是没有得到回应。
That evening, she tried again.
当天晚上，她再次做出尝试。
As she arrived, two men were delivering
bread and newspapers.
她到的时候，有两个人在送面包和报纸。
She was in.
她进去了。
Corday pretended she was an informer
and gave Marat a list of traitors.
科迪假装是线人，给了马拉一份叛徒的名单。
''I will have them guillotined in a week'', he said.
“一周之内，我就把他们送上断头台“，他说。
And that was it.
就这样，
Out came the knife, straight into Marat's chest.
亮出匕首，直插入马拉的胸膛。
So the Friend of the People
was lost to the Revolution.
就这样人民的朋友亡于革命。
Inside the National Convention,
grief-stricken deputies cried their eyes out,
在国民大会中，悲痛欲绝的代表们恨不得把眼珠子哭出来，
authentically or not.
真假难辨。
What they most wanted, I think,
was for Marat to come back to them.
他们最希望的，我认为，是马拉能够活过来。
''Come back, come back.
We need you, all of France needs you.''
回来吧，回来吧，我们需要你，整个法国需要你。
And then one of the most theatrical deputies
rose to his feet and shouted,
然后一个最戏剧化的代表站了起来大声喊道：
''David, where are you?
There is one more job for you.''
“大卫，你在哪儿呢？这里有份工作交给你。“
And David of the swollen cheek
miraculously found his voice.
肿脸颊大卫奇迹般地找回了自己的声音。
I shall do it.
我一定
''I shall do it, ''he said.
“我一定“，他说。
''I will paint Marat. ''
我会把马拉画下来。
It was midsummer,
the hottest in anyone's memory.
正值仲夏，所有人的记忆中最热的一回。
The embalmers, under David's direction,
were working overtime,
防腐师们，在大卫的指导下，加班加点
preparing Marat's body for the funeral.
把马拉的尸体做葬礼准备。
But his normally ghastly red-flesh colour
was rapidly turning green.
但是他平时那可怕的肉红色正迅速变绿。
David had wanted Marat displayed sitting upright,
working for the good of the people.
大卫本希望马拉能够坐正，展示为人民不辞辛劳的样子，
But the decomposing corpse
refused to co-operate.
但是快速分解的尸体不肯配合。
Drenched in perfume, it had to be laid flat out
for the grieving public to file past.
尸身浸透了香水，只能平放着，让悲伤的群众绕过。
The funeral would inevitably fade
in people's memory.
葬礼会不可避免地从人们的记忆中消退，
The painting, though, would never fade.
而画作，将永远留存。
It was Marat's best revenge,
它简直是马拉最好的报复，
for it would make sure
that he would always be around.
他因为这幅画而永远伴随着我们。
Here was someone transfigured by goodness,
honesty and patriotic selflessness.
画面上是一个善良、诚实和无私的爱国精神的化身。
''Look upon him,'' David is saying,
''And you will see the highest type of humanity.''
“看着他，“大卫仿佛在说，”你就会看到人性的最高形式。“
He's cleaned Marat up, of course.
自然，大卫也把马拉的身体清理得很干净。
The skin has the colour of cool stone,
皮肤是冰冷的石头色，
the wound is unmissable,
yet at the same time almost delicate,
伤口非常明显，同时又有点太精致了，
like the incision in the side of Christ on the cross.
仿佛十字架上基督的伤口。
The white sheets seem shroud-like,
白色的床单看起来像裹尸布，
ghostly wrappings of the great man
as he hovers between our world and posterity.
朦胧地包裹着这位大人物，使他漂浮于现世与后世之间。
It's a cult image,
这是一幅邪典图画，
and it tells you to believe.
要求你要相信它。
Its genius lies in the fact
that it's also a story for the people.
其天才之处在于，这同时又是一个人民的故事。
For once, the hero isn't Roman, he's one of them.
这一回，英雄人物并非罗马人，而是他们中的一员。
It's the first great work for the faces in the crowd,
这是群众面孔的第一幅重要作品，
the singers of the Marseillaise.
唱着马赛曲的群众。
You can almost feel David
imagining whole families in front of this painting,
几乎可以想见大卫如何想象一家人站在画作前面，
a father saying to his children,
''Look, there's his inkwell."
父亲对孩子们说，“看，这是他的墨水瓶。“
''Look, there's the letter of the wicked Corday,
stained with the blood of the good Marat.''
“看，这里是那个邪恶的科迪的信，上面还沾着善良的马拉的血。“
But David is not showing the letter
that got Corday into Marat's house,
只不过，大卫并没有展示那封使科迪进入马拉家的，
the one with the list of traitors.
上面列出叛徒名字的信。
It's a different letter.
这是另外一封信。
One that would make Marat seem
like a victim of his own kindness.
这封信让马拉似乎因为自己的善良而受害。
''It's enough that I am truly unhappy
to have the right to your benevolence, '' it says.
“这样受恩于您，我真的很不开心。这就够了“，上面写着。
On top of the box is another letter,
from the widow of a soldier fallen in battle.
在盒子上还有另外一封信，来自阵亡战士的遗孀，
With it is a donation Marat is about to send her.
旁边使马拉准备捐给她的钱。
Two women, then,
the good mother and the bad Corday.
两位女性，一个好妈妈，一个坏科迪。
There's no attempt
to give a sense of Marat's room here.
作品完全没有尝试描绘马拉的房间。
No crossed pistols hanging on the wall,
no fake columns.
墙上没有交叉的手枪，也没有假柱子。
Instead, the entire top half of the painting
is filled with loose, feathery strokes
取而代之的是，充满画面整个上半部分的松散的羽毛笔触，
that could be wall or just indeterminate space.
可能是墙，也可能是不确定的虚空，
The space of forever.
永恒的空间。
But then that box, grainy, solid.
但是还有那个盒子，粗糙而坚固。
''He was one of you, '' the box says.
''One of the poor and suffering.
“他是你们的一员“，盒子在诉说，”跟你们一样穷困，跟你们受苦。“
''But now you can't reach him.
“如今你再也见不到他了。
''No one can, except through this. ''
“谁都见不到，除了在这里。”
But even while you're held spellbound,
但即使你被迷住，
another voice inside your head says,
''Hold on a minute,"
还有另外一个声音在耳边说，“等一下，”
''this is the purest witchcraft.''
“这是彻头彻尾的巫术”
What David has done here is to glorify a paranoid,
“大卫这是在美化一个偏执狂，
whose greatest satisfaction
was the persecution of thousands of people
“这家伙最大的满足是对成千上万人进行迫害“
whose only crime was to be lukewarm
about politics.
“而他们唯一的罪过，不过是对政治不冷不热“
This is an accomplice of terror.
“这是与恐怖的共谋“
Of course, it never occurred to David
that he was betraying art.
当然，大卫从来没有想过自己是在背叛艺术。
''Oh, no,'' he would have said.
''I'm fulfilling its highest, noblest purpose,"
“哦，不对。“他会说，”我是在实现艺术的最崇高的目标：“
''that of moral re-education."
“道德教化“
''That's what all those altarpieces
that once hung in churches did,"
“正如教堂的圣坛上悬挂的那些作品一样，“
''but those were all lies and fairytales."
“只不过他们画的都是谎言和神话。“
''We have a new church now,
the church of revolutionary virtue. ''
“而我们现在有了新的教堂，革命精神的教堂。“
So why do I like David?
所以，我为什么喜欢大卫？
Well, I don't. He's a monster.
实际上，我不喜欢，他就是个怪物。
But he makes ideas blaze in dry ice.
他能够让信念在干冰中燃烧。
He is a fantastic propagandist, no one better.
他是一个超级宣传员，无人超越。
Albert Speer could just as well roll over and die.
Albert Speer也只能瞠乎其后。
And what was the point of it all?
那么这些又有什么意义呢？
Well, it's a revenge on wit, on chat and on banter.
我想，这是对机敏、巧言和戏谑的回击。
But it was more than that.
还不止于此。
This is art designed
to make those who saw it virtuous citizens.
这是一种将观赏者塑造为高尚公民的艺术。
And it's all so perfect, so tragic,
so poetic you almost believe it.
而它又如此完美，如此富于悲剧色彩，如此诗意，你几乎要相信它了。
But like a lot of art designed to improve humanity,
但正如很多致力于提高人性的艺术一样，
it has the opposite effect.
它起到了相反的效果。
Because it's a lie.
因为它本来就是谎言。
Three months after the assassination of Marat,
马拉遇刺三个月之后，
on October 16th, 1793,
Marie Antoinette went to the guillotine.
1793年10月16日，玛丽安特瓦奈特被押去断头台。
David saw her tumbrel going down the street,
大卫看到她的囚车在街上走，
while people spat in their hands
人们摩拳擦掌
and tried to throw the gobs
on the woman who'd been queen.
争相往他们曾经的王后身上扔东西。
He sketched her impassively.
他描绘了她的形象，内心无动于衷。
But David's got more important things on his mind
than the fate of Marie Antoinette.
在大卫心中有比玛丽安特瓦奈特的命运更重要的事情。
He's now the official director
of revolutionary propaganda,
他现在是正式的革命宣传主管
to the exclusion of practically everything else.
其它任何事情都无需关心。
When his wife disapproved of his zeal,
he divorced her.
当他的妻子不赞成他的热诚时，他跟她离婚了。
David has become an enforcer,
sitting on the Committee for General Security,
大卫成了执法者，是总体安全委员会的成员。
hunting down the treacherously half-hearted,
signing warrants for their execution.
忙于追捕那些三心二意的背叛者，签署他们的处决令。
The terror had begun,
恐怖已然开始，
and David had become part
of the great engine of killing.
大卫成了绞肉机的一部分。
And as the tempo of the guillotine got faster,
随着断头台的鼓点越催越快，
David busied himself with ever more
extravagant spectacles to educate the people.
大卫忙于用越来越夸张的奇观来教育民众。
Casts of thousands, massed singing virgins,
statues on the site of the Bastille.
几千人出场，成群唱歌的处女，巴士底上方的雕像，
A festival of the supreme being,
至高级别的欢庆，
starring the high priest of the Revolution,
Maximilien Robespierre.
主演是大革命的祭司，马克西米连罗伯斯比尔。
In the end, David was a victim of his own success.
最终，大卫成了他自己成功的牺牲品。
The hard-nosed men who were running the war
knew that bread and guns mattered,
负责战争的强硬人物清楚，跟面包和枪炮相比，
and virgins and doves didn't.
处女和鸽子没那么重要。
So David wasn't just a distraction,
he was a menace. Get rid of him.
所以大卫不仅分散注意力，还是一个威胁。赶走他！
And David's downfall
was inextricably linked to the fate of Robespierre.
大卫的垮台与罗伯斯庇尔的命运密不可分。
Increasingly, Robespierre was spoken of
罗伯斯庇尔越来越经常被视为暴君，
not as saviour of the Revolution, but tyrant,
而不再是革命的救世主。
and David, the window-dresser of his tyranny,
was going down with him.
而大卫，罗伯斯庇尔的妆点师，必须跟他一起走人。
Robespierre was attacked in the Convention,
the dreaded words ''outside the law'' uttered.
罗伯斯庇尔在国民大会受到攻击，有人说出了“违法“这样吓人的词汇。
Incredulous, David made a spectacle of himself.
难以置信的是，大卫在此时展示了自己。
''Robespierre,'' he shouted.
“罗伯斯庇尔“，他喊道。
''If you drink the hemlock, I will drink it with you. ''
“如果你喝毒药，我就跟你一块儿喝“
But of course, he didn't.
不过，他当然没有一块儿喝。
The next day, David was suddenly indisposed,
so he missed his own date with martyrdom.
第二天，大卫突然身体不适，错过了殉道的时机。
He was not there beside Robespierre
when he was guillotined
罗伯斯庇尔上断头台的时候，
and the blade at last came down on the terror.
刀刃终于落在恐怖统治者头上的时候，大卫不在他的旁边。
But they came for David, nonetheless.
但大卫最终也没有逃过去。
Vilified as tyrant of the arts,
David tried to stammer a defence.
被诋为艺术的暴君，大卫结结巴巴地为自己辩护。
No one could understand what he was saying,
but they noticed how pale he was,
没人听得懂他说的话，但人们注意到他面色苍白，
how the sweat ran through his clothes
and dripped onto the floor.
汗水渗透衣服，滴落在地上。
In prison, he managed to get hold of some paints
and he painted this self-portrait.
在监狱里，他设法弄到了一些颜料，给自己花了这幅自画像。
You can see the famous tumour
and the twist it gives to his face,
可以看到那个知名的肿瘤，和他脸上的扭曲，
but that's as far as the truth goes.
但是忠于事实的部分到此为止。
Because what we're seeing
is not the old propaganda master, that's for sure,
因为我们看到的，肯定不是那个老年的宣传大师
but young David, 20 years at least taken off,
而是大卫年轻时候的样子，至少年轻了20岁，
all innocent, hair romantically dishevelled,
单纯透顶，头发漫卷，
coat open to expose his pure, transparent heart.
外套敞开，露出纯洁、清澈的内心。
And he's done himself with palette and brushes.
他用画笔和调色板成就了自己。
''Why me?'' it says.
“为什么惩罚我？“它问。
''I'm just a painter. ''
“我只是个画家“
Yeah, right.
好吧，没错。
Led astray, were you? Just doing your job?
误入歧途，对吗？你只是在做自己的工作？
I don't think so.
少来了。
But guess what? The art plea worked.
但你猜怎么着？艺术请求奏效了。
David got out of prison,
大卫出狱了，
and spent the next years doing spectacular,
uncontroversial portraits like this.
在接下来的岁月里创作这样壮观的，毫无争议的肖像画。
Monsieur Seriziat, his brother-in-law.
赛力齐亚特先生，他的姐夫。
This is what the Revolution of the virtuous
had become,
这就是高尚革命的结果，
the Republican tricolour
reduced to a fashion accessory.
共和国的三色旗沦为时尚装饰。
When he does do history paintings,
they're pleas to stop killing.
再画历史事件的时候，他们展现的都是制止杀戮的情景。
No more politics, then,
for Jacques-Louis David, right?
雅克路易大卫再不涉及政治了，是吗？
Wrong.
不对
The old demon never really goes away.
老恶魔永远不会真正消失。
Once bitten by power, you stay bitten.
被权力咬伤过一次，就永远被咬伤。
He airbrushed Marat,
why shouldn't he airbrush Napoleon?
他能够粉饰马拉，为什么不能粉饰拿破仑？
When Napoleon was crowned emperor in 1805,
拿破仑在1805年加冕为皇帝的时候，
David was slavishly at his side, official glamoriser.
大卫忠实地站在旁边，他是官方的
But then, of course, Napoleon was defeated,
the monarchy restored.
当然，后来，拿破仑被打败了。王室又恢复了。
Lots of Napoleon-lovers were forgiven,
很多拿破仑的追随者都被原谅了，
but not David.
但是其中不包括大卫。
He'd done something that could never be forgiven.
他干过无法被原谅的事情。
He'd done this,
他画了这幅画，
the most notorious image produced by the terror.
恐怖统治下产生的最臭名昭著的形象。
France had had enough of Jacques-Louis David.
法国受够了雅克路易大卫。
Banished from his own country,
David ended up here in Brussels,
被驱逐出自己的国家，大卫最终来到布鲁塞尔这里，
where he did paintings
of increasingly high-gloss weirdness,
在这里他画了一些越来越高光泽的怪异作品。
a big fish in a very small pond.
才华无处施展。
In France, they mostly talked about him
as a back number,
在法国，人们主要把他作为过期杂志谈起，
''Oh, David, Brutus and all that. Isn't he dead?''
“哦，大卫，画过布鲁图斯等等那个。他死了吗？“
When he did die, in December, 1825,
当他在1825年十二月去世的时候，
the government in Paris refused permission
for his family to bring the body home.
巴黎的政府拒绝许可其家人将遗体带回家。
No king-killers allowed.
“弑君者不得回家“
David's paintings, though, were up for sale.
但是大卫的画，还在出售。
Before that, they were put on public display.
Not, however, the notorious Marat.
之前，他们就可以公开展出，当然，除了臭名昭著的马拉之死。
That was kept under guard
at the artist's son's house.
马拉之死被保管在大卫儿子的房子里。
Admission by private arrangement.
只能私人安排参观。
And you take a look at it and you know why.
看一眼就明白为什么了。
If ever there was a work of art
that says that beauty can be lethal,
如果说真有意见艺术品展示了美可以致命，
it's Jacques-Louis David's Death of Marat.
那就是雅克路易大卫的马拉之死。